<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against lukwarmenesse in religion. Preached at Saint Maries in Oxford, the sixt of September, 1640. / By Henry Wilkinson, Batchelour in Divinity of Magdalen Hall. Printed by order from the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1616-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2238B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E204_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15190</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859817</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111916</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96522)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 36:E204[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against lukwarmenesse in religion. Preached at Saint Maries in Oxford, the sixt of September, 1640. / By Henry Wilkinson, Batchelour in Divinity of Magdalen Hall. Printed by order from the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1616-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Beale, for Humphrey Robinson, and are to be sold at the Signe of the three Pigeons in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an initial blank leaf.</note>
                  <note>Thomason copy imperfect: some bleed-through of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation III, 16 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111916:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111916:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST LUKWARMENESSE in <hi>RELIGION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PREACHED AT SAINT MARIES in OXFORD, the Sixt of <hi>September,</hi> 1640.</p>
            <p>By HENRY WILKINSON, Batchelour in Divinity of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen Hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by order from the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>John Beale,</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the three <hi>Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111916:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111916:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE houſe of Commons, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Should never have preſumed to prefixe the name of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Houſe to my Sermon, had I not beene incouraged ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, both by your protection and approbation. For though it was my hard lot to be ſuſpended for preaching of it, (how juſtly you</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:111916:3"/> 
               <hi>have ſeene) yet it was my happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to have beene releaſed by you. As for the entertainement and uſage which both I and my Sermon have found from ſome, I wholly paſſe them over in ſilence, let it ſuffice that by the</hi> Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae <hi>of this Honourable Court, I was freed from the cenſure impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on me, and by your</hi> Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur, <hi>it is now become</hi> publici juris. Plinius Secundus <hi>in his Epiſtle to</hi> Veſpaſian <hi>ſayes, that many things ſeeme very precious for this very reaſon</hi> quia templis ſunt dicata: <hi>and we know how that the Goats hayre and Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers skins though of ſmall value in themſelves, yet did contract a reverent eſteeme; being once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated
<pb facs="tcp:111916:3"/> to the Sanctuary. So this Sermon, which (that I may uſe the</hi> Epigrammatiſts <hi>word to</hi> Domician) <hi>from you hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> vitam id eſt famam, <hi>and which now caſts it ſelfe at your tribunall, rejoycing to bear your Cogniſance, may for this very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe of your name which is</hi> praeſidium &amp; dulce decus meum, <hi>find better acceptance, and a greater eſtimate, then it can challenge by any merit of its owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The onely tribute which I can returne, is to beſeech Almighty God that he would be pleaſed to vouchſafe the gracious influence of his holy Spirit unto you, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſucceſſe of your councels</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:111916:4"/> 
               <hi>may be as happie, as the hopes, and expectations be great: Let the beautie of the Lord be upon you, and eſtabliſh the Worke of your hands upon us: This is the earneſt praier of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, HENRY WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111916:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>REVEL. 3. 16.</bibl>
               <q>So then becauſe thou art Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme, and neither cold nor hot, I will ſpew thee out of my Mouth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are the words of Chriſt to the Angell of the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> who though he direct his ſpeech chiefly to the Miniſters of that Church, (for ſo ſome underſtand the word <hi>Angel</hi> to involve the whole company of Miniſters) yet it is to be underſtood as having relation to the people committed to their charge, which appeares from that ſpeech ſo often repeated; Hee that hath an Eare, let him heare what
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111916:5"/> the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</p>
            <p>Here in theſe words is a Fault detected, and a Judgment denounced, and the reaſon why that judgment is threatned againſt that Fault: The ſin is Lukewarmeneſſe in Religion, the judgement is ſpewing out of the mouth of Chriſt, and the reaſon, why this judgement is threatned againſt this Fault, it may bee drawne from the ſinne it ſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmeneſſe, for many ſinnes carry their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their foreheads: Now Gods ſpeech here is by way of ſimilitude, taken from Meat, and the Stomack: it is obſerved, how that thoſe meats, which are either hot or cold are better kept in the ſtomack by reaſon of the abounding quality of heat, and coldneſſe; which ſtirre the ſtomack to embrace them more kindly, and more eaſily to digeſt them. But lukewarme meats by reaſon of their mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle temper, as they doe not move ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſenſe at their firſt entrance, ſo being in the ſtomack, they lye unconcocted, and at length are vomitted up againe: Here then we may ſee the greatneſſe of the ſinne by the grievouſneſſe of the puniſhment: He ſaith, he will ſpew them out of his Mouth: this intimates, he cannot abide them any longer, he nauſeates them, as the ſtomacke doth meats, which it can neither endure, nor retaine; it intimates alſo the loathſome fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy condition of ſuch a people, how that he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111916:5"/> will never have reſpect unto ſuch a people, or ſuch a perſon: for without all doubt God will not looke at his vomit any more: what leſſe to be indured in the ſtomacke, than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted meate? What leſſe to be imbraced, than vomit? What more to be loathed?</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee what is meant by thoſe three words in the text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Firſt he is ſaid to be <hi>Frigidus,</hi> cold for matter of Religion, who is not at all moved to ſee good duties neglected, the Ordinances of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, or the honour of God abuſed: who though perhaps he be a Chriſtian, yet he is indifferent, for the entertaining of any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as well as the true. Secondly, hee is ſaid to be <hi>Fervidus,</hi> hot, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> fervent in ſpirit, as it was ſaid of <hi>Apollos, Act.</hi> 18. 25. To which fervency of Spirit we are exhorted in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 11. Such a one hath his heart warmed with the love of Chriſt, by which he boyles (as it were like ſeething wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) with a deſire of doing good, or with indignation to vindicate the honor of Chriſt: But thirdly, hee is <hi>Tepidus,</hi> lukewarme, that doth partake of both extreames, and is of a middle temper betwixt both, and as God complaines of <hi>Ephraim, Hoſ.</hi> 7. 8. that he was a Cake not turned, baked on one ſide and dough on the other, betwixt roaſted and raw, he abſtaines from foule and enormous ſins, and ſo he gaines the repute of a civill honeſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111916:6"/> Man: he labours to keepe a faire correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on both ſides, and to that purpoſe, hee doth apply himſelfe to ſeverall Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe now is to ſhew you the beſt and worſt of Chriſtians: the worſt is the lukewarme profeſſour, who ſeemes better than he is; the beſt is the zealous profeſſour, who is better than he ſeemes; as for him that is ſtarke cold, I ſhall ſpeake of him onely by way of compariſon to the lukewarme. And therefore, Firſt I will ſhew reaſons why this lukewarme Chriſtian ſhould be in the worſt condition. Secondly, I will diſcover that ſin, by comparing it with the vertue in the Text, included in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the handling of which I ſhall ſhew the nature and condition of true zeale. Thirdly, I will take a view of divers <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaean</hi> profeſſours, with their fallacies and impoſtures.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> That this lukewarme temper in Religion is <note place="margin">Why this Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the worſt.</note> the worſt, it appeares, not onely from that fearefull judgement expreſſed, by ſpewing out of Gods Mouth, to which they lye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, which are of it; but alſo from the wiſh, which Chriſt makes in the verſe before my Text; I would (ſaith he) thou wert either hot or cold (v. 15.) I would thou wert either what thou doſt make a ſhew off, or elſe, that thou didſt not make a ſhew of what thou art not.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111916:6"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But here it may be objected, that the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle temper is the beſt, it being in the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vertue, and <hi>Tepiditas</hi> if it be not the beſt, yet it comes neerer the beſt, than that which is quite cold.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſponſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What ever may be ſaid of morall vertues, that they conſiſt in the middle, yet I am ſure, that this kind of Mediocrity hath no place here: For our love to God, and zeale to the truth can never be too intenſe, nor doe I ſee how any vertue in its formall reaſon can be too much intended, or admit of an exceſſe; for a man cannot be ſaid to be <hi>Nimis liberalis,</hi> though he may be ſaid to be <hi>Nimius in largitione:</hi> Then whereas it is ſaid, that <hi>Tepor</hi> comes neerer heat, than coldneſſe; and ſo it is the better temper; I anſwer, it doth not follow in this buſineſſe of Religion: for every ſin is by ſo much the greater, by how much the more grace hath abounded: now where there is <hi>tepor,</hi> it is a ſigne that the heat of grace hath ſomewhat thawed the coldneſſe of their hearts, which is another reaſon, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> why this middle temper of all other is the worſt: Nothing makes ſin ſo exceeding ſinfull, as the abuſe or neglect, or contempt of grace: for this reaſon <hi>Chorazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida</hi> are in far worſe ſtate, than <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon, Mat.</hi> 11. 21, 22. Though they were moſt Idolatrous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. So alſo the condemnation of <hi>Capernaum</hi> ſhall bee farre more heavy than <hi>Sodom's</hi> or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111916:7"/> 
               <hi>Gomorrah's,</hi> becauſe they never had the meanes offered, as had the former. As for thoſe that are lukewarme, they have been in the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Goſpel, many of them have had common illumination, and taſted of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly gift, and have beene made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted of the good Word of God, and of the powers of the World to come, if theſe fall away, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to renew them againe unto repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 4, 5, 6. So alſo that ground, which after it hath dranke in the Rayne, yet bringeth forth bryars and thornes, is reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and is nigh unto curſing, whoſe end is to be burned, in the ſame Chapter. So it is here, he which hath beene vouchſafed ſo much grace, as to know his Maſters will, and yet doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes. As for thoſe that never came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt, nor have not arived ſo farre as a temporary faith, they are in a farre better caſe than thoſe other: For he which comes ſo farre as to be convinced in his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the goodneſſe and equity of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and is perſwaded of the excellency of it, and likewiſe hath ſome conflicts in his conſcience concerning the profeſſion of it, yet for all this he is in <hi>Aequilibrio,</hi> hee is in ſuſpence, whether he ſhould goe through all difficulties, whether he ſhould withſtand all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111916:7"/> oppoſitions in his profeſſion, he is that dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-minded man, that Saint <hi>James</hi> ſpeakes of, that is unſtable in all his wayes; let not ſuch a one expect to receive any thing at the hands of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 7, 8. They are like him that received the ſeed into ſtony places, for ſuch a man heares the Word, and anon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it, and that with joy; yet he hath not root in himſelfe, but endureth for a while: For when tribulation and perſecution come for the Word, he is offended at it; or elſe he is like him that received it among thornes, in whom the cares of this World, and the deceitfulneſſe of riches choake the Word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 20, 21. As for thoſe men, that go ſo farre, as to make ſome outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, but yet dare not in all points goe through with it; they betray the cauſe and make ſhipwracke of the faith: God ſpeakes plainely by his Prophet, If God bee God, then follow him; if <hi>Baal</hi> be God, then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: This middle way, this halting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two opinions is ſure to be wrong; the extreames both are ſure to be better, and one is ſure to be right.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this middle way is the worſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are hated on both ſides, that are of it: God, he hates them, becauſe they are no better, and the other part hates them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſo good; both the contrary ſides thinke themſelves wronged, whilſt they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111916:8"/> have but a part, when they expect the whole. For whileſt he performes ſome dutyes and that (as he would ſeeme) out of conſcience; thoſe that make no conſcience of any duty, count him a <hi>Puritan;</hi> and whileſt hee doth theſe ſervices to God but feynedly, God counts him an Hypocrite: Such kind of men are they amongſt us, that are neither found Proteſtants, nor downe-right Papiſts: one ſide dares not, the other ſide will not truſt them; but neither loves them truely. It is juſt with them, as it was with <hi>Servilius</hi> in <hi>Rome:</hi> for the Hiſtorian ſpeaking of P. <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilius,</hi> and <hi>Appius,</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Servilius medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſe gerendo, nec plebis vetuit odium, nec apud patres gratiam inijt:</hi> He neither avoyded the hatred of the Commons of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor did he gaine the favour of the Senate: But <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> carrying himſelfe baſely, but not indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, <hi>Patribus mire fuit gratus,</hi> was in high favour with the Senate. Wherefore the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Suetonius</hi> is very good: <hi>Quando non effugias, quin alterum habiturus ſic inimicum, aut ſocium jacienda tunc eſt alea, alterutri adhaerendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt:</hi> When it cannot be avoided but that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt have each of them thy friend or thy confederate, caſt thy dice and adhere to one. He ſpeaks it of a warre between two Princes; it holds good here: Wherefore that ſtate which doth engage me in the hatred of both ſides, muſt needs be the worſt; but by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111916:8"/> joyning to neither, I gaine the hatred and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy of both: So that meere politicke reſpects, (which commonly worke moſt with our moderate men,) ſhould diſſwade them from this temper: if they did but conſult their owne ſafety, they would betake themſelves to one extreame. But it is the pollicy of thoſe men not to engage themſelves farre in any matters of Religion by a manifeſt and open Declaration of their opinion, or publiſhing their intentions, becauſe then they muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goe through ſtoutly, or fall ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: theſe men that thus hover betwixt the Ballances, have not courage enough, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to commend them to any ſide, as to gaine the favour of it: But as <hi>Fabius Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> Captaine to <hi>Velleius,</hi> when he heard of the revolting of the Navy at <hi>Ravenna,</hi> being in ſuſpence what way to take, <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith thus of him; <hi>Utrumque conſilium aſpernatus eſt,</hi> he rejected that councell which ſhould have engaged him on one ſide, <hi>et quod inter ancipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia deterrimum eſt, nec auſus eſt ſatis, nec provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit:</hi> And which in doubtfull caſes is worſt of all, he neither had courage enough to goe through with his buſineſſe, nor wiſedome enough to provide for his owne ſafety. It is juſt ſo with theſe men: they have not courage enough to embarke themſelves heartily on one ſide, nor providence enough to prevent the hatred of both.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111916:9"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, this middle lukewarme conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution is the worſe in regard, they loſe the honour of their actions, and the reward of all their labours: What the Comaedian ſaith of one in love, is true alſo here, <hi>veram ſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipias, neque gnaviter perficias, nihilo plus agas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>quam ſi operam des, uteum ratione inſantas.</hi> He that begins and doth not finiſh he doth little better than diſcover a reaſonable madnes. As for him that is quite cold in his Religion, as he takes no paines in the ſervice of God, ſo he ſcarce lookes for any reward: We ſhall have many lukewarme Profeſſours, that goe very farre in the profeſſion of Religion, and are very ſtrict in the outward performance of holy duties, ſo that it may bee ſaid, of ſome of them, as it was of him in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, they are not farre from the Kingdome of Heaven; and yet for want of going fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and aduancing forward, and preſſing toward the marke of the high calling, they fall ſhort of the goale: for when the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous turneth away from his righteouſneſſe, and committeth iniquity, and doth according to all the abhominations of the wicked, ſhall hee live? in his treſpaſſe that he hath treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, and in his ſinne that he hath ſinned, in them ſhall he dye, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 24. As en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes eſpecially if weighty, ſhould never be raſhly attempted: ſo if they be once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, they ſhould bee proſecuted with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111916:9"/> that ſo they may be diſpatched with ſucceſſe. Theſe lukewarme men are like mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Chapmen, that have a good mind to buy a bargaine, but are loth to goe to the price of it: now he that bids five hundred pound for that which is worth a thouſand pound, ſhall goe without it, as well as hee that bids nothing: In this buſineſſe wee ſhould be like the Merchant in the Goſpel, that ſold all that be had, to buy the Jewell of rich price. Chriſt is a jewell infinitely beyond all that we can give, and therefore we cannot offer leſſe, then our whole ſelves, all our ſervices, and performances, all our labours and endeavours: Theſe lukewarme Men can be content to afford Chriſt a cap and a knee, but they will not give him their heart, nay they are very ſcrupulous in mint and rue, and very exact in the Ceremony; and (as if Religion were a Comedy) they will in voyce, and geſture act divine duties, though in their heares they renounce; and in their lives deny the parts they play: Give me leave to interrogate: Why have theſe men gone ſo farre, as to get a forme of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, but will not goe one ſtep further, as to ſhew the power of it? Why will they take ſo much paines to perſonate, and act a Chriſtian, and not to be one? Why did they taſte of heavenly myſteries, and not digeſt them? Why doe they take on them the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111916:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:111916:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111916:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111916:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111916:12"/> of Chriſts ſouldiers, and goe into the field and endure ſome skirmiſhes, and yet reſolve not to march on, and to fight the good fight, and finiſh their courſe? This is to take a great deale of paines to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Yee did run well (ſaith the Apoſtle) who did hinder you that you ſhould not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the truth? <hi>Gal.</hi> 15. 7. Have yee ſuffered ſo many things in vaine? <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 4. Were it nor farre better to bee either hot, (that is) having enflamed affections, and ardent zeale to the truth, by which a man goes on with courage and reſolution, continues with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſtancy, and ends with honour; and ſo receives the crowne of his labours, and guerdon of his patience? or elſe to be cold, ſecurely purſuing irreligious affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without denying ones ſelfe the pleaſure of any ſinne, by the interruption of holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? But theſe tepid men who make ſome kind of conſcience of praying, but pray fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they take paines to be denyed: <hi>Qui ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midè rogat, docet negare:</hi> He that prayes fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, begs a denyall; thoſe that doe the worke of God, but doe it negligently, labour for a curſe; for curſed is every one that doth the work of the Lord negligently. He that ſerves God with a ceremony and complement on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his ſervice ſhall bee recompenced with that anſwer, <hi>Iſay</hi> 1. 12. Who hath required this at your hand, to tread my Court? The
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111916:12"/> truth is, theſe men take paines to aggrauate their owne condemnation: For, if Religion be a good cauſe, why doe theſe men goe ſo coldly about it? and if it be a bad, why doe not they wholy diſclaime it? For better it were either to be cold, and ſuch a one who as he hath no piety, ſo he makes no ſhew of any; or elſe to be hot (that is) zealous, truly ſuch as hee profeſſeth himſelfe to be; farre better it is to be one of the former, then to counterfeit a perſon which he is not, and ſo (as <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Antipater,</hi> who being a vitious man, yet did uſe to weare a white cloake, the enſigne of innocency) <hi>virtutis ſtragulam pudefacere,</hi> to put honeſty to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſhame.</p>
            <p>In the next place I will make a further diſcovery of the greatneſſe of this ſinne, by comparing it with its contrary vertue, which is included in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Text, which is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred hot, and is interpreted in the 19. verſ. by zealous: I will now ſhew what true zeale is, by which lukewarmeneſſe will appeare in its proper colours.</p>
            <p>Zeale is a mixt Affection of love an anger, <note place="margin">What zeale is.</note> by which a man is ſtirred up to the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of true Religion, by doing what good he can to promote it, and oppoſing any ill, that may hinder it: It hath reſpect both to good and its contrary, and produceth effects both of love and hatred; of love to the former,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111916:13"/> and hatred to the contrary: now this hatred againſt ſinne, if it cannot conquer it, yet it begets an inward griefe, and vexation of heart for evils cannot reforme. Thus <hi>David</hi> did not onely keepe gods law himſelfe, but he ſhed abundance of teares becauſe others did not keepe Gods Law, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 136. <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> wiſhed his head was a fountaine of teares, that he might weep for the ſinnes of the people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 1. Thus <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was moſt zealous in the reforming of the abuſes of Gods worſhip, Chap. 13. Thus did the zeale of <hi>Phineas</hi> appeare in executing the judgement ſpeedily, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in <hi>Moſes,</hi> our Saviour, and in <hi>Paul,</hi> who were in a manner tranſported with ſacred zeale.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But why ſo zealous (ſome will ſay?) What needs all this heate? A man may come to Heaven without marching furiouſly like <hi>Jehu?</hi> Doe we not ſee many by their too much heate have become <hi>Phaeton's,</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries to Church and State, and ſet al in combuſtion? It is not for every one to be carried to Heaven in a fiery Chariot with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijah.</hi> Methinks a moderation might ſerve, there may very well be an abatement of this heate, it may remit of its degrees, and bee brought to an equall temper: for doe wee not ſee in our bodies, how overmuch heate enflames the blood, and diſtempers the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſy of the whole?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111916:13"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no queſtion but there is much diſcretion to be uſed in the managing of our zeale: but diſcretion doth not abate the heat of love, but direct it: prudence doth not remit our diligence and zeale, but guide it. It is not the duty of prudence to caſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to quench or coole this affection: Hee which is in a right courſe and goes ſlowly, is not moderate, but idle: for we muſt not goe, but run the wayes of Gods commandements: Beſides, if we looke but upon good dnties, or upon good men, we ſhall find ſomething extraordinary, which commends them to God, you ſhall have ever ſomething to execude: Prayer is ſaid to prevaile, if it be fervent, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 16. We muſt love God, but it muſt be with all our heart: it is not every faith, but faith working by love, that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: there is a worke of faith, a labour of love, a patience of hope, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. 3. Chriſt will have none to follow him, but him that will lay downe his life for him. The Apoſtle exhorting the Corinthians to Heavenly, and ſpiritual graces, uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, deſire ſpirituall gifts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 31. it is not a lazy vote, but an earneſt coveting of them, which obtaines thoſe things at the hands of God, ſo it is not the profeſſion of Religion God looks at, but the earneſt zealous profeſſion: and Chriſt is ſaid to have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111916:14"/> dyed to purifie to himſelfe, a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple zealous of good workes, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 14. It is not the <hi>opus operatum,</hi> that he delights in, for then hee would never have ſaid to the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> When you ſpread forth your <note place="margin">Iſ. 1. 15.</note> hands, I will hide mine eyes, and when you make many prayers, I will not heare; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in that Chapter he refuſeth all their ſervices; for when men performe good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, doing them with a kind of reluctancy God refuſeth them. A Boy learnes his book, but hee doth it rather for feare of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, than for love of learning: So it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly with men, they doe religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, but they doe them as a taske impoſed which they are loath to omit, but they are glad when they are done. Then look upon Chriſt and his Saints, you ſhall ſtill finde ſomething ſuperlative in them; we ſhould be alwayes looking upon Chriſt as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and finiſher of our faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2. What ever was in him, was moſt abſolute; you ſhall alwayes finde his ſervants indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to expreſſe him as neare to the life as poſſibly they can: Others may ſeeke to enter and faile, but we muſt ſtrive; you ſhall find <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtling till day breake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 24. And <hi>Habakuk</hi> watching, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 1. to ſee what the Lord would ſay unto him: It was not an ordinary zeale, that made <hi>David</hi> to pray, and praiſe the Lord ſo often in a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111916:14"/> day, or <hi>Daniel</hi> to faſt ſo frequently, or <hi>Paul</hi> to take ſo much paines to beate downe his body, to keepe it in ſubjection: It was more then ordinary love to Chriſt that made <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> ſpeake what they had heard, and ſeene concerning him, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. or that made them rejoyce, that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for his Name, Chap. 5. It was a ſtrong faith that made thoſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 35. rather to chuſe to be tortured, than to accept deliverance when it was offered, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering farre more willingly, than the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary could inflict cruelly: There is no think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Mediocrity,</hi> when we looke upon Chriſt the Archetypum, and his Saints tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the leſſen he hath ſet them, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating his Copy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But ſome will ſay, that there is much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and impoſture, and the Devill doth make men many times beleeve that they are truly zealous, when indeed they are but like Comets, which burne very hot for a time, but at length end in a ſmoake: and it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that there is a miſguided zeale which as it is very hot, ſo it is very perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> My anſwer to this ſhall be by way of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Symptomes of true zeale.</note> diſcovery of the truth of zeale, and firſt; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> True zeale hath ever knowledge as its guide; and fanctity of life, as its attendant and fruit: And he that hath a good mixture of zeale,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111916:15"/> and knowledge, ſo that his zeale doth quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his knowledge, and his knowledge doth guide his zeale, is like a ſhip well ballaſted, that ſayles with a proſperous gale: Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge without zeale puffes a man up, and zeale without knowledge is like the Devill in the poſſeſſed,, which caſts him ſometimes into the fire, and ſometimes into the water: ſuch was the zeale of <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſion; ſuch was the zeale of the Jewes of whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 2. that they had a zeale, but not according to knowledge. Then true zeale hath ever ſanctity as its fruit; for as zeale without knowledge is frantick, ſo without knowledge it is hypocriticall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sympt. </seg>2</label> 2. We may know true zeale by its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, it ariſeth from a heart repleniſhed with flames of love to Chriſt, which as they were at the firſt kindled by the holy Spirit, ſo are they afterwards blowne and continued by it. But there is another kinde of zeale, which ariſeth from a heart diſtempered with paſſion: the former is a conſtant and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent heate, like that on the Altar, or like the Veſtall fire, which was alwayes kept burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: The other is but like a flaſh, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from ſome ſuddaine turbulent paſſion, which being ſpent, it dyes. The beſt men are ſometimes ſubject to ſuch diſtempers, thus <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> when they would needs have fire commanded from Heaven, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111916:15"/> thoſe that denyed entertainement to our Saviour; were rebuked for their zeale, by our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. Thus many doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake a good cauſe, rather out of faction and humour, or out of hatred to a perſon, than love to CHRIST or zeale to the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sympt. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, as you may know true zeale from its beginning, ſo from its aime, and end too; True zeale ever aimes at Gods glory, and the advancement of true Religion: whereas if you ſeparate the zeale of moſt men from colaterall by-reſpects, from vaine-glory, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, revenge, and the like, you ſhall have it faint and flagge, and at length wholly deſiſt. One would have thought the zeale of <hi>Jehu</hi> to have out ſtript <hi>Joſiah</hi> in vindicating the honour of God, and yet what <hi>Jehu</hi> did, it is thought was rather out of ſome reſpects of his owne, for eſtabliſhing the Crowne on his owne head, or for revenge, or the like; for it is ſaid of <hi>Jehu,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10. 31. that <hi>Jehu</hi> tooke no heed to walke in the Law of the Lord God of Iſrael with all his heart, for he departed not from the ſinnes of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam,</hi> that made Iſrael to ſinne: this is it that deceives many, they thinke that they be truly zealous, becauſe they doe good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties frequently, and perhaps willingly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed they doe them, but not to a right end, but for ſome colaterall reſpects. For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111916:16"/> a command of God may concurre with ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpects of our owne: for it is Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that we ſhould heare the word preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that we ſhould pray; but in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of both theſe duties, wee may have ſelfe-reſpects of our owne: for wee may come to heare the Preacher, as they in the Goſpell did come to heare our Saviour, to entrap him in his ſpeech; and to informe againſt him: or we may come to heare him, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did to heare Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> for his eloquence: or we may come to heare him, as ſome ſcoffers uſe to doe, to laugh at him: And we may pray as the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> did, to get a good opinion of men, or to ſatisfie locall ſtatutes, or out of cuſtome, faſhion, or to comply with men: but he doth a good duty zealouſly, who will doe it when all ſelfe-reſpects be layd aſide; when a man will heare the Word, though he be reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and pray with <hi>Daniel,</hi> though hee be in danger of his life: He that can doe a duty when there is nothing to encourage to the duty, when it is left naked; nay, when it is diſcountenanced, diſcouraged, puniſhed, it is an evident ſigne, that it was the zeale to the end that carryed him through all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in the paſſage.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sympt. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, zeale if it be true is of a moſt maſculine diſengaged couragious Nature, free from all baſe and ſervile feares, it yeelds
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111916:16"/> to no encounters, but it is encreaſed by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, juſt like heate ſurrounded with cold it recollects it forces, and at length breakes forth with greater violence: Such was <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiahs</hi> zeale, Chap. 6. he would not flye, though it were to ſave his life: What? ſhall ſuch a man as I fly? <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate knew well enough the conſtitution of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans zeale, and therefore at length he would not vouchſafe them the honour of an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: for he knew well, that their zeale was ſuch, as that it would triumph over all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; but he tooke a farre more dangerous courſe, for he ſought by flattery, and faire promiſes to drawe them to Paganiſme. Wherefore a Chriſtian ſhould alwayes ſay thus: Shall I that am a Chriſtian, ſhall I deny my cauſe? Shall I betray my faith becauſe it finds many perſecutours? Shall I alter my judgement, becauſe ſome men are of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary mind? Shall I change my opinion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Hoc Ithacus velit?</hi> Shall I remit of my diligence, and ſtrictneſſe of life, for feare of a ſrowne, or ſtroke of abloquie? Theſe be baſe and unworthy reſpects farre below a Chriſtians: And it is certaine, that they which ſtand in ſo much awe of men, are not <hi>recti in curia</hi> with God: for zeale if it be diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, it is ſo bold as to attempt good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with difficulties. It was zeale thus tempered, that lived in the hearts of thoſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111916:17"/> primitive Chriſtians, who were mirrours in their time, aſtoniſhments to their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and examples of wiſedome and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to all poſterity: of whom <hi>Sulpitious Severus</hi> ſpeaking, ſayes thus of them, Lib. 2. <hi>Multò avidiùs tunc martyria glorioſis morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quaerebant, quàm nunc Epiſcopatus pravis ambitionibus appetuntur:</hi> They did ſeek more greedily after Martyrdome, than ſome did ambitiouſly after Biſhopricks: It was this zeale, that cauſed <hi>Ignatius Antioch</hi> ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire death, ſaying <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Oh that I might enjoy thoſe wild beaſts prepared for my death! Let all the torments of the World come upon me, ſo that I may enjoy Chriſt. Let but our lukewarme profeſſour compare his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and temper with this which I have now deſcribed, and then hee may ſee how farre ſhort he fals of his duty though he ſeemes to goe beyond it.</p>
            <p>In the next place I come to take a ſurvey of divers ſorts of Chriſtians, ſome of which will come within the compaſſe of this judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt there is the idle, lazy, and negligent profeſſour, who takes himſelfe to be as good as he ſhould be, becauſe he is not ſo bad as other men, juſt like the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who ſaith, Lord, I am not as other men; I am no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner, no drunkard no adulterer, &amp;c.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111916:17"/> And I would we could all ſay ſo truly: thus whileſt they meaſure themſelves by the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities of others; they never come to know the rectitude of vertue, or their owne deformities: Their goodneſſe much conſiſts in negatives, and they take themſelves to be good enough, becauſe they be not ſtark nought; the beſt that you can ſay of them, is that which <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Galba,</hi> that he was <hi>magis extra vitia, quam cum virtutibus,</hi> they are rather not notoriouſly ill, than ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good: But if this negative goodneſſe would ſerve the turne, than that abjurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Goſpell, was unſeaſonable: Why ſtand ye here idle? theſe men were doing no hurt, but it is hurt enough that they were doing no good: <hi>Meroz</hi> was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that bitterly <hi>Judges</hi> 5. 23. becauſe they came not out to helpe the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mighty: It is not ſufficient to doe the people of God no hurt, but wee muſt doe them good, we muſt engage our ſelves in Chriſts quarrell: for hee that is a Neuter or Indifferent, hee is an enemy: hee that is not with me, (ſaith Chriſt) he is againſt me. It is not this lazy profeſſing of Chriſt, or the title of a Chriſtian, that will ſerve the turne, but the zealous profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is that that he lookes at: A tree if it be barren or unfruitfull is caſt out of the garden, as well as bryer, and Thornes, nor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111916:18"/> will it ſuffice to bring forth leaves but no fruit: for the figtree was curſed, that had leaves but no fruit: So that the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſhew of a formall profeſſion will not ſerve the turne: this is to bring forth leaves but no fruit: Let but thoſe men conſider whether there be the ſame minde in them, as there was in Chriſt, <hi>Philippians</hi> 2. 5. which ſhould be in us all. Let them but conſider, whether Chriſt would content himſelfe with a negative goodneſſe, whether he would ſtand ſtill and ſay nothing, when he ſhould ſee good duties neglected, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſſions reviled, and men live in ſenſuality and carnall luſts. Let them alſo conſider how that God complaines, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. not of thoſe that ſet themſelves againſt the truth, but that there was no man had cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for the truth. I make no queſtion but <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> had kept his head on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, if he could have beene contented to have ſaid nothing concerning the inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous marriage of <hi>Herod</hi> with his brother <hi>Philips</hi> wife: I doubt not but that <hi>Mordecai</hi> might have had the favour both of <hi>Naman</hi> and the King, if ſo be he would have bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his knee. Both <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> had eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped impriſonment, if they could but have held their tongues: But to the ſilent, when Gods glory ſuffers; is to be acceſſary. Thoſe in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. that wandred up and downe in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111916:18"/> Sheepskins, and goatskins, being deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, afflicted and tormented, I doubte not, but if they would have contented themſelves with this negative kinde of goodneſſe, they might have gone in better clothes, and found better uſage. But thoſe were ſuch as were ready to fulfill the whole Law of God, not onely in not doing ill, but in doing good, though they were ſure to be evill intreated: Let but ſuch men as count their lives deare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, when they ſee Religion lye a bleeding, holineſſe of life become a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, zealous profeſſours reproached, and men ſeparated from all imitable qualities advanced, Haereſies favoured, and truth with-held in unrighteouſneſſe; let theſe I ſay, that count their lives, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty or goods deare vnto them, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how that the fearefull are put in the forefront of all thoſe that have their parts in the Lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone; <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. 8. Let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member likewiſe, why our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 25. He that will thus ſaye his life, ſhall looſe it. How farre are theſe Men from counting it all joy, when they fall into diverſe temptations? <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But you will ſay, that the times were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver worſe, it never farre harder with good men.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:111916:19"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We will grant all this, now is the time of tryall; for remember what our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8. 31. He that is aſhamed of me, and my words in an evill and adulterous generation (it is an evill and adulterous generation, that puts a man upon his tryall) of him will I be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But you will ſay, I ſhall be accounted ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, I ſhall be thought to walke alone.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This was juſt <hi>Elijah's</hi> caſe: He knew of none that did worſhip the God of Iſrael but himſelfe: Let us never give God cauſe to complaine, as once he did, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 30. I ſought for a man among them, that ſhould make up the hedge, and ſtand in the gap before mee, for the Land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it, but I found none: Where is the courage and conſtancy of Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> who for his conſtant and bold defending the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arrian Haeriſie, being threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned death by <hi>Valence</hi> the Emperour, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Oh that I might dye for the truth! But when they ſaw that threatning would doe no good, they then ſought by flattery to corrupt him; but he told them, that he was not ſo to bee wrought upon, he was reſolved neither for feare, nor flattery to betray either a good cauſe, or a good conſcience: The
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111916:19"/> true tryall of a Chriſtians love and zeale to the truth, is when ones goods, or his credit, or his life comes incompetition, when once it comes to this, that a man muſt leave all and follow Chriſt, it is to be feared, that many who have farre leſſe to loſe, then the rich man in the Goſpell, will goe away farre more ſad: When once it comes to this; that if you ſticke to Chriſt in ſuch a cauſe, you ſhall be turned out of the Synagogue; when once it comes to turning out, it is alſo to be feared, that many who did beleeve in Chriſt as thoſe did, <hi>John</hi> 12. 42, 43. yet will not dare to confeſſe him, but will with them rather chuſe the praiſe of men, than of God. You would thinke the lukewarme profeſſour to be a very good Chriſtian, till he come to his tryall; and then hee diſcovers himſelfe what he is: for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that man that hath his heart fixed on any ſinne, hee will diſpence with his Religion, when once it comes to croſſe him in it: Some men have their <hi>Herodias,</hi> their <hi>Dalilah;</hi> others have their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lords, they muſt bee all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: others have great livings, thoſe muſt bee kept. <hi>Pilate</hi> was very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deliver Chriſt to the fury of the Jewes to bee crudified; and yet for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111916:20"/> feare of <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſayes one Evangeliſt, and to content the people ſaith another, for feare of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the ſatisfaction of the People (two potent arguments) he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers him to bee crucified: Their is no diſcovering of a lukewarme Profeſſour, till he be put upon ſome Criticall point, and then he will doe as thoſe did, <hi>John</hi> 6. 66. they will goe backe and walke no more with Chriſt: they can be contented to follow Chriſt: but when once it comes to take up the Croſſe and follow him; Oh then they are offended: They will be accounted profeſſours of the Goſpell, as it is a Goſpell of peace, and as it brings glad tidings, and promiſeth Salvation: but when it comes to be made good, that whoſoever will live godly in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus muſt ſuffer perſecution, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3. 12. When once it comes to bee fulfilled in them, the World will hate them, then Chriſt becomes a ſtumbling-blocke; then Religion becomes a ſcandall: Theſe men would ſerve God, but they would ſerve as good cheape as they could, and with as little paines as may be: For if it come to a matter of coſt, then have they a <hi>quor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum perditio haec?</hi> to what purpoſe is all this coſt? if of paines, O then <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> this is a hard ſaying, who can
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111916:20"/> beare it? Let but theſe men compare their zeale to Chriſt, with the zeale and love that men uſually beſtow on their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impolyments, and they ſhall find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much outſtript: We ſee how that men ordinarily can be content to riſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and late to take reſt, and eate the bread of ſorrow; and yet the lukewarme Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian will not deprive himſelfe of the leaſt contentment and ſatisfaction, he will by no meanes defraud his Genius in any thing: We ſee men faſt tyed to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts, being in a manner captiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their owne imployments, and yet it is a kind of bondage, and abridgement of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to devote ones ſelfe to the ſervice of Chriſt: Let them looke upon ſinners in the proſecution of their luſts; and let them bluſh to be outgone by them: When any ſinne is enſhrined in thy heart, with what facility doth it command all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, as its vaſſals, and yet with what difficultie and reluctancy hath God any ſervice? Sinfull objects do inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with admirations and ſatisfactions, attracting the deſires and inclinations af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them: They enter into their play, their ſerious buſineſſe, their ſleepe, their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they take up their diſcourſe, reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh their memory, enflame their deſires:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111916:21"/> And behold how little theſe lukewarme men are affected with ſpirituall objects! Thus can men be content to nouriſh fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and burning coales in their boſome, but cannot endure a ſparke of zeale: How farre are ſuch men from being tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with an holy extaſie, with the Spouſe in the <hi>Canticles!</hi> How farre from being ſicke with love, from being raviſhed with the beauty of Chriſt? Lord, what ſhowres of teares can they beſtow upon any tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory loſſe, but not a drop that they ſpare for the loſſe of our Beloved! What ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent deſires, what flames can they ſend after their ſinnes, and how dull, how ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh in ſeekeing him whom our ſoule ſhould love! Let but theſe lazy negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Chriſtians conſider this and bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, there is another ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who though they meane well, yet are much to be blamed, who doe too much trouble themſelves in ſmall matters, not worthy the contending for: they are too contentious about the Mint and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, and with <hi>Peter</hi> they draw the ſword, when it were farre fitter it were in the ſcabbard. To what purpoſe is it, either to beſtow much hatred, or much love about matters not worthy our conſideration?
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111916:21"/> What is this, but to call for a ſword to kill a fly, or to make a mountaine of a mole-hill? farre better it were to reſerve our hotteſt zeale for greateſt matters: for why ſhould we put our whole ſtrength to that which may be blowne away with a blaſt, or moved with a finger?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, as thoſe are blame-worthy that are ſo violent in ſmall matters, ſo thoſe are as bad, or worſe, that are little moved when great matters come in queſtion: Many there be, that undertake a good cauſe ſo faintly, as if they were afraid leſt thoſe words which the wench ſpoke to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſhould be ſaid to them; ſurely thou alſo art one of them: they can be contented to be profeſſours, but they would not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Galilaeans:</hi> Thoſe words which the blind man ſpake to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> ſtumble many a man, Wil yee alſo be his Diſciples? His Diſciples they would bee, but they would not have much notice taken of them: But thoſe words of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> when once they came to be ignominiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogated, they doe not onely ſtumble many, but make them fall too. What? are yee alſo deceived? Doe any of the Rulers or <hi>Phariſees</hi> beleeve on him? When once it comes thus to be ſaid by ſome kind of men: What? are yee alſo deceived? are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111916:22"/> you led away by ſuch men in ſuch a cauſe? I tooke you to have had more diſcretion: doe you ſee any of the great Doctors of your Mind? Such words as theſe doe for ever ſtop the mouthes of thoſe (who with <hi>Agrippa</hi> were almoſt perſwaded) for ever opening in ſuch a cauſe againe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, there is the politick Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the reſerved profeſſour, that never ſhewes himſelfe but at halfe-lights: You can have little or no hold of him, and in matters of controverſie he leaves himſelfe without obſervation: He never unvailes himſelfe in publick, but in ſuch a cauſe, wherein he is ſure of countenance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: He obſerves ſome rules of <hi>Matthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avel,</hi> which he is reſolved that the rules of Chriſtianity ſhall never croſſe, becauſe he will make theſe ſtoop to them: He is fixed in this, he will never doe any thing or ſpeak any thing which may enterfeire with his hopes or prejudice his preferments, and that he will make the beſt uſe of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (that is to ſay) the beſt advantage. Few or none can tell, what to make of this man, nor doe I beleeve he knowes what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion he is of himſelfe: But queſtionleſſe all ſides are deceived in him, if they take him to be wholly theirs. I found this man in the clouds, and there I leave him.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:111916:22"/>
            <p>Since there be ſo many deceits and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures in our profeſſion, it concerns us to examine of what temper we are: Wee muſt feele our owne pulſe, and try how it beates; we ſhould ſee whether our zeale be ſuch as God will accept: For we ſee that many ſet out of Aegypt, and travell well on their journey, yet never come to the Land of Canaan: many that ſet their faces to Sion and Jeruſalem, yet never arrive there; many that ſet out of the Port with a faire gale, yet make Shipwrack before they come to the Haven: many, who with <hi>Orpah</hi> leave <hi>Moab</hi> with a reſolution never to returne againe, yet <hi>Naomi</hi> alleadging ſome world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reaſon, they do goe back: few with <hi>Ruth</hi> outſtand all difficulties in the paſſage.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let us ſet before our eyes the examples of the beſt, and let vs be anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and encouraged by them: and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the worſt of Apoſtates, and let us be warned by them; and then let us ſet before us our owne ſelves, and ſee whether we have not done our beſt at firſt: If thou be advanced from ſome low condition to ſome dignity, which ſhould ever bee the ſeat of Vertue, then try whether thy edge to Religion be not blunted, whether thy zeale be not abated, and whether as thou haſt outſtrip thy equals in place, ſo thou
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111916:23"/> doſt in merit: For if the change in thee be ſuch as it was in <hi>Galba,</hi> of whom it was ſaid, that he was thought to be <hi>omnium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dignus temperio, niſi imperaſſet,</hi> worthy of the Empire till he had it, then I muſt needs ſay that he hath purchaſed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment at too deare a rate, that paid his honeſty to get it: But if it may be ſaid of thee, as it was of <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> that he was <hi>mutatus in melius,</hi> made better by his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, if thy heart be for humility lower, and zeale hotter, then it was before, if thy advancement prove the vantage ground, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to exalt thy vertues then thy ſelfe; then mayeſt thou aſſure thy ſelfe of the love and favour of God, as well as thou haſt honour of men: But if it fall out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, men will be apt to thinke that thou hadſt leſſe of the Ballaſt and more of the fayle, and that thou madſt more haſt, then good ſpeed to thy preferment.</p>
            <p>It is a ſhrewd ſinge of a lukewarme tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, when men make ſome conſcience of performing holy duties, but they doe them as if they were about ſome other buſineſſe: When they come to Gods ſanctuary with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſolemnity and preparation to meet the Lord, when they heare the Word without affection and reverence, when they pray without fervency and intention; nay, when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111916:23"/> they can without any regreat omit theſe duties to ſatisfie their luſts, when they can omit the will of God and doe their owne, when men take offence at their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren becauſe of their ſtrictneſſe and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of life, <hi>When wee ſee men halting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and Baal, endeavouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile betwixt Rome, and the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, joyniug the Ephod and the Teraphin, and ſetting up the Arke and Dagon together; When we heare the language of Canaan, and the language of Aſhdod, both proceed out of the ſame mouth, as it was in Nehemiahs time,</hi> Chap. 13. 24. When we ſee ſilver become droſſe, and wine mixed with water, as God complaines, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 22. When we ſee the holy oyntement of pure myrthe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. to bee compounded; and the Lamps of the Tabernacle that ſhould burne cleare to be choaked and ſuffocated with groſſe vapours, and the fine flower to bee mixed with branne; and thoſe that ſhould handle the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as of ſincerity, doe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſophiſticate the word, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 17. When we ſee men yoaking of the Oxe and the Aſſe together, and wearing linnen, and woollen garments, uſing the name of <hi>Jebi,</hi> and the name of <hi>Baali,</hi> which is forbidden, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 17. When we ſee men profeſſing true Religion, and the ſervice
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111916:24"/> of one God, dividing themſelves, ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and Mammon; others betwixt God and their belly; a third, betwixt God and ſome adored <hi>Hellen;</hi> a fourth betwixt God and his <hi>Mecaenas;</hi> a fifth, betwixt God and the world. When we ſee a divorce made, where there ſhould be an inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble union (that is) betwixt God and the heart, and an union made, where there ſhould be an eternall divorce (that is) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the heart and the creature; when we ſee a mixture in theſe things which ſhould be moſt ſimple and pure; when the Mint and the Cummin are more ſtood upon, than the greater things of the Law, and men are more ſcrupulous in obſerving the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Elders, then the Doctrine of Chriſt, being moſt ſuperſtitious in things not commanded, and yet moſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in things neceſſary, ambitiouſly ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the charge of ſoules, and yet moſt negligent in looking to their charg, crying out, <hi>Templum Domini, Templum Domini,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing caring for the Lord of the Temple; <hi>When we ſee pictures preferred before their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>totypes, and Saints days honoured above his day, that is the Lord of Saints; When we ſee men bowing the knee to Chriſt, and yet crucifying him in their lives,</hi> profeſſing to know God, but in their workes denying him; When a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111916:24"/> heat of profeſſing is turned into a heat of diſputing; and matters of faith are made matters of controverſie, and diſcourſe of Religion hath almoſt turned out the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it; <hi>When we ſee old Haereticks revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and exploded errours new dreſſed; When we ſee brainſick fancies are broached and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced for Truth, and novelty hath turned out Antiquity;</hi> When I ſay ſuch things as theſe doe occurre either in a Church or perſon; when we ſee ſuch Symptomes as theſe, it will be no hard matter to gueſſe at the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and conſtitution.</p>
            <p>I ſhould in the next place come to ſpeak of the judgment; <note n="*" place="margin">The occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe words was the report that the Scots had taken New Caſtle.</note> but I fear that this part of my Text is taken out of my hands, and is already begun to be put in execution: I feare, I may too truely ſay, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> did, that the Lord hath opened his Armory, and brought forth the weapons of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. 25. God grant that part of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Prophecy, Chap. 23. 33. be not begun to bee fulfilled in us: thou ſhalt be filled with drunkenneſſe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, with the cup of aſtoniſhment and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. But for my part I had rather be an Evangeliſt to bring glad tydings, then a <hi>Faecialis,</hi> to denounce Gods judgements: VVherefore in the laſt place conſider how grievous this ſin is, and how dreadfull is its
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111916:25"/> puniſhment, and tremble at the one, and abhorre the other. If therebe but a ſparke of zeale, let us blow it into a flame: If zeale be languid, or the heat remiſſe, let us dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and intend it: For it is the heat of love and a heart repleniſhed with flames, and it is zeale as ſtrong as death, and moſt intenſe affections; it is a ſoule raviſht with love and an heart tranſported with an holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacy, that Chriſt delights in. VVhat e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we render unto him, it muſt be totall and it muſt be ſuperlative: if we love him, we muſt love nothing elſe; he will have no rivals in our afflictions: if we ſerve him we muſt ſerve him alone; he will have no partners in his worſhip. Hee that offers leſſe then all to him, who infinitly deſerves more than all that we can offer, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>values him. Hee therefore that gives to Chriſt the halt the lame and the blind; a halting heart, lame affections, and blind devotion: Hee that thinkes his lukewarme love, his languid zeale, or his faint performance will ſerve the turne, he offers the greateſt contempt, and the higheſt indignity to the Sonne of God. VVherefore let us beſeech Almighty God, that he would bee pleaſed to put his holy Spirit into our hearts, to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and quicken our ſoules by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111916:25"/> working of the Holy Ghoſt, that ſo we may ſerve him with ardent zeale, ſtrong affections, and love enflamed, alwayes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on with courage and reſolution, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing with patience and conſtancy, that ſo we may end with glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
